<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2020 on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/</link><description>Recent content in 2020 on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>STACKIT Kubernetes Engine with Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/12.03-stackit-kubernetes-engine-with-gardener/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/12.03-stackit-kubernetes-engine-with-gardener/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://stackit.de/en/">STACKIT&lt;/a> is a digital brand of Europe’s biggest retailer, the Schwarz Group, which consists of Lidl, Kaufland, as well as production and recycling companies. Following the industry trend, the Schwarz Group is in the process of a digital transformation. STACKIT enables this transformation by helping to modernize the internal IT of the company branches.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-stackit-and-the-stackit-kubernetes-engine-ske">What is STACKIT and the STACKIT Kubernetes Engine (SKE)?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>STACKIT started with colocation solutions for internal and external customers in Europe-based data centers, which was then expanded to a full cloud platform stack providing an IaaS layer with VMs, storage and network, as well as a PaaS layer including Cloud Foundry and a growing set of cloud services, like databases, messaging, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener v1.13 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.23-gardener-v1.13-released/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.23-gardener-v1.13-released/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dear community, we&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce a new minor release of Gardener, in fact, the 16th in 2020!
v1.13 came out just today after a couple of weeks of code improvements and feature implementations.
As usual, this blog post provides brief summaries for the most notable changes that we introduce with this version.
Behind the scenes (and not explicitly highlighted below) we are progressing on internal code restructurings and refactorings to ease further extensions and to enhance development productivity.
Speaking of those: You might be interested in watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4sQs_Hj6xpY">the recording of the last Gardener Community Meeting&lt;/a> which includes a detailed session for &lt;a href="https://github.com/gardener/terraformer/releases/tag/v2.0.0-rc.0">v2 of Terraformer&lt;/a>, a complete rewrite in Golang, and improved state handling.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Case Study: Migrating ETCD Volumes in Production</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.20-case-study-migrating-etcd-volumes-in-production/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.20-case-study-migrating-etcd-volumes-in-production/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote class="alert alert-note">
 &lt;div class="alert-title">
 &lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24" width="24" height="24">&lt;title>information-outline&lt;/title>&lt;path d="M11,9H13V7H11M12,20C7.59,20 4,16.41 4,12C4,7.59 7.59,4 12,4C16.41,4 20,7.59 20,12C20,16.41 16.41,20 12,20M12,2A10,10 0 0,0 2,12A10,10 0 0,0 12,22A10,10 0 0,0 22,12A10,10 0 0,0 12,2M11,17H13V11H11V17Z" />&lt;/svg>
 &lt;p>
 
 Note
 
 &lt;/p>
 &lt;/div>
 &lt;p>This is a guest commentary from &lt;span style="white-space:nowrap">&lt;a href="https://metal-stack.io/">metal-stack&lt;/a>&lt;/span>.&lt;br>&lt;br>metal-stack is a software that provides an API for provisioning and managing physical servers in the data center. To categorize this product, the terms &amp;ldquo;Metal-as-a-Service&amp;rdquo; (MaaS) or &amp;ldquo;bare metal cloud&amp;rdquo; are commonly used.&lt;/p>

 &lt;/blockquote>

&lt;p>One reason that you stumbled upon this blog post could be that you saw errors like the following in your ETCD instances:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener v1.11 and v1.12 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.04-gardener-v1.11-and-v1.12-released/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/11.04-gardener-v1.11-and-v1.12-released/</guid><description>&lt;p>Two months after our last Gardener release update, we are happy again to present release v1.11 and v1.12 in this blog post. Control plane migration, load balancer consolidation, and new security features are just a few topics we progressed with. As always, a detailed list of features, improvements, and bug fixes can be found in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/gardener/gardener/releases">release notes&lt;/a> of each release. If you are going to update from a previous Gardener version, please take the time to go through the action items in the release notes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener Integrates with KubeVirt</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/10.19-gardener-integrates-with-kubevirt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/10.19-gardener-integrates-with-kubevirt/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Gardener team is happy to announce that &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud">Gardener&lt;/a> now offers support for an additional, often requested, infrastructure/virtualization technology, namely &lt;a href="https://kubevirt.io/">KubeVirt&lt;/a>! Gardener can now provide &lt;a href="https://github.com/cncf/k8s-conformance">Kubernetes-conformant&lt;/a> clusters using KubeVirt managed Virtual Machines in the environment of your choice. This integration has been tested and works with any qualified Kubernetes (provider) cluster that is compatibly configured to host the required KubeVirt components, in particular for example &lt;a href="https://www.openshift.com/blog/openshift-virtualization-containers-kvm-and-your-vms">Red Hat OpenShift Virtualization&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gardener enables Kubernetes consumers to centralize and operate efficiently homogenous Kubernetes clusters across different IaaS providers and even private environments. This way the same cloud-based application version can be hosted and operated by its vendor or consumer on a variety of infrastructures. When a new customer or your development team demands for a new infrastructure provider, Gardener helps you to quickly and easily on-board your workload. Furthermore, on this new infrastructure, Gardener keeps the seamless Kubernetes management experience for your Kubernetes operators, while upholding the consistency of the CI/CD pipeline of your software development team.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shoot Reconciliation Details</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/10.19-shoot-reconciliation-details/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/10.19-shoot-reconciliation-details/</guid><description>&lt;p>Do you want to understand how Gardener creates and updates Kubernetes clusters (Shoots)?
Well, it&amp;rsquo;s complicated, but if you are not afraid of large diagrams and are a visual learner like me, this might be useful to you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this blog post I will share a technical diagram which attempts to tie together the various components involved when Gardener creates a Kubernetes cluster.
I have created and curated the diagram, which visualizes the Shoot reconciliation flow since I started developing on Gardener.
Aside from serving as a memory aid for myself, I created it in hopes that it may potentially help contributors to understand a core piece of the complex Gardener machinery.
Please be advised that the diagram and components involved are large.
Although it can be easily divided into multiple diagrams, I want to show all the components and connections in a single diagram to create an overview of the reconciliation flow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener v1.9 and v1.10 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/09.11-gardener-v1.9-and-v1.10-released/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/09.11-gardener-v1.9-and-v1.10-released/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summer holidays aren&amp;rsquo;t over yet, still, the Gardener community was able to release two new minor versions in the past weeks.
Despite being limited in capacity these days, we were able to reach some major milestones, like adding Kubernetes v1.19 support and the long-delayed automated gardenlet certificate rotation.
Whilst we continue to work on topics related to scalability, robustness, and better observability, we agreed to adjust our focus a little more into the areas of development productivity, code quality and unit/integration testing for the upcoming releases.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener v1.8.0 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/08.06-gardener-v1.8.0-released/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/08.06-gardener-v1.8.0-released/</guid><description>&lt;p>Even if we are in the midst of the summer holidays, a new Gardener release came out yesterday: v1.8.0! It&amp;rsquo;s main themes are the large change of our logging stack to Loki (which was already explained in detail on a &lt;a href="https://grafana.com/blog/2020/07/15/gardener-saps-kubernetes-as-a-service-open-source-project-is-moving-its-logging-stack-to-loki/">blog post on grafana.com&lt;/a>), more configuration options to optimize the utilization of a shoot, node-local DNS, new project roles, and significant improvements for the Kubernetes client that Gardener uses to interact with the many different clusters.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PingCAP’s Experience in Implementing Their Managed TiDB Service with Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/05.27-pingcaps-experience/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/05.27-pingcaps-experience/</guid><description>&lt;p>Gardener is showing successful collaboration with its growing community of contributors and adopters. With this come some success stories, including PingCAP using Gardener to implement its managed service.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="about-pingcap-and-its-tidb-cloud">About PingCAP and Its TiDB Cloud&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://pingcap.com/about/">PingCAP&lt;/a> started in 2015, when three seasoned infrastructure engineers working at leading Internet companies got sick and tired of the way databases were managed, scaled and maintained. Seeing no good solution on the market, they decided to build their own - the open-source way. With the help of a first-class team and hundreds of contributors from around the globe, PingCAP is building a distributed NewSQL, hybrid transactional and analytical processing (HTAP) database.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New Website, Same Green Flower</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/05.11-new-website-same-green-flower/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2020/05.11-new-website-same-green-flower/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud">Gardener project website&lt;/a> just received a serious facelift. Here are some of the highlights:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A completely new landing page&lt;/strong>, emphasizing both on Gardener&amp;rsquo;s value proposition and the open community behind it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The Community page&lt;/strong> was reconstructed for quick access to the various community channels and will soon merge the Adopters page. It will provide a better insight into success stories from the community.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improved blogs&lt;/strong> layout. One-click sharing options are available starting with simple URL copy link and twitter button and others will closely follow up. While we are at it, give it a try. Spread the word.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Website builds&lt;/strong> also got to a new level with:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>