<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2021 on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/</link><description>Recent content in 2021 on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Happy Anniversary, Gardener! Three Years of Open Source Kubernetes Management</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/02.01-happy-anniversary-gardener/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/02.01-happy-anniversary-gardener/</guid><description>&lt;p>Happy New Year Gardeners!
As we greet 2021, we also celebrate Gardener’s third anniversary. Gardener was born with its first open source
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gardener/gardener/commit/d9619d01845db8c7105d27596fdb7563158effe1">commit&lt;/a>
on 10.1.2018 (its inception within SAP was of course some 9 months earlier):&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-text" data-lang="text">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>commit d9619d01845db8c7105d27596fdb7563158effe1
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>Author: Gardener Development Community &amp;lt;gardener.opensource@sap.com&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>Date: Wed Jan 10 13:07:09 2018 +0100
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> Initial version of gardener
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> This is the initial contribution to the Open Source Gardener project.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Looking back, three years down the line, the project initiators were working towards a special goal: Publishing Gardener as an open source project on Github.com.
Join us as we look back at how it all began, the challenges Gardener aims to solve, and why open source and the community was and is the project’s key enabler.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Machine Controller Manager</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/01.25-machine-controller-manager/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2021/01.25-machine-controller-manager/</guid><description>&lt;p>Kubernetes is a cloud-native enabler built around the principles for a resilient, manageable, observable, highly automated, loosely coupled system. We know that Kubernetes is infrastructure agnostic with the help of a provider specific &lt;a href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/architecture/cloud-controller/">Cloud Controller Manager&lt;/a>. But Kubernetes has explicitly externalized the management of the nodes. Once they appear - correctly configured - in the cluster, Kubernetes can use them. If nodes fail, Kubernetes can&amp;rsquo;t do anything about it, external tooling is required. But every tool, every provider is different. So, why not elevate node management to a first class Kubernetes citizen? Why not create a Kubernetes native resource that manages machines just like pods? Such an approach is brought to you by the &lt;a href="https://github.com/gardener/machine-controller-manager">Machine Controller Manager&lt;/a> (aka MCM), which, of course, is an open sourced project. MCM gives you the following benefits:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>