<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What's Gardener Project to SAP?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/news/004/00/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/news/004/00/</guid><description>What&amp;rsquo;s Gardener Project to SAP? An New Article on about SAP, Gardener and OSS. Recently, Thomas Hertz, CNCF board member and head of Development Experience at SAP, published an overview article at the TheNewStack where he discusses projct Gardener and its place in SAP and the open source community, and what&amp;rsquo;s the future ahead of it.
&amp;ldquo;Gardener is an SAP-driven open source project that tackles real-world demands for hyperscale Kubernetes services, regardless of infrastructure.</description></item><item><title>Gardener Website 2.0</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/news/002/00/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/news/002/00/</guid><description>.news-item .green-power { color: #0f674e; font-weight: 700; } .news-item .green-power img { display: inline-block; width: 32px; vertical-align: middle; margin: 0 5px 0; } @media (min-width: 750px) { .news-item .green-power img { width: 48px; } } .news-item .title-2 { font-weight: 700; background-color: unset!important; color: #222!important; } New Website, Same Green Power! The Gardener Project just got a brand new website with multiple improvements and we are all very excited!</description></item><item><title>Gardener 1.4.0 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/news/003/release/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/news/003/release/</guid><description>Gardener Release 1.4 ​ The Gardener release 1.4 is mainly focused on stability improvments and optimizations. For example, we twitched some configurations (e.g CPU and memory limits), and improved the monitoring and healtchechks. And there are some new features too. The list below is an overview of the most notable changes. Explore the full release notes in GitHub Release 1.4. ​​
Notable Changes Now you decide when the reconciliation happens if you change your Shoot specification ​ Previously whenever you change a configuration of your Shoot.</description></item><item><title>Gardener 1.3.0 Released</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/news/001/release/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/news/001/release/</guid><description>Gardener 1.3.0 Released See what&amp;rsquo;s new and noteworthy presented by the team on the regular community meeting recording.
Bookmark the agenda for upcomming community meetings and stay up to date with what&amp;rsquo;s going on in the project.
For a detailed list of changes refer to the release notes.
Enjoy!</description></item></channel></rss>