<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2022 on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/</link><description>Recent content in 2022 on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Community Call - Get more computing power in Gardener by overcoming Kubelet limitations with CRI-resource-manager</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.20-gardener-community-meeting-october-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.20-gardener-community-meeting-october-2/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/ppalucki">Pawel Palucki&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/kad">Alexander D. Kanevskiy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="topics">Topics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Alexander Kanevskiy begins the community call by giving an overview of &lt;a href="https://github.com/intel/cri-resource-manager">CRI-resource-manager&lt;/a>, describing it as a &amp;ldquo;hardware aware container runtime&amp;rdquo;, and also going over what it brings to the user in terms of features and policies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pawel Palucki continues by giving details on the policy that will later be used in the demo and the use case demonstrated in it. He then goes over the &amp;ldquo;must have&amp;rdquo; features of any extension - observability and the ability to deploy and configure objects with it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Community Call - Cilium / Isovalent Presentation</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.06-gardener-community-meeting-october/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.06-gardener-community-meeting-october/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/raymonddejong">Raymond de Jong&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="topics">Topics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This meeting explores the uses of &lt;a href="https://cilium.io/">Cilium&lt;/a>, an open source software used to secure the network connectivity between application services deployed using Kubernetes, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/cilium/hubble/blob/master/README.md">Hubble&lt;/a>, the networking and security observability platform built on top of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Raymond de Jong begins the meeting by giving an introduction of Cillium and eBPF and how they are both used in Kubernetes networking and services. He then goes over the ways of running Cillium - either by using a supported cloud provider or by CNI chaining.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Community Call - Gardener Extension Development</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/06.17-gardener-community-meeting-june/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/06.17-gardener-community-meeting-june/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/jensac">Jens Schneider&lt;/a> and Lothar Gesslein.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Starting the development of a new Gardener extension can be challenging, when you are not an expert in the Gardener ecosystem yet. Therefore, the first half of this community call led by Jens Schneider aims to provide a &amp;ldquo;getting started tutorial&amp;rdquo; at a beginner level. &lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en">23Technologies&lt;/a> have developed a minimal working example for Gardener extensions, &lt;a href="https://github.com/23technologies/gardener-extension-mwe">gardener-extension-mwe&lt;/a>, hosted in a Github repository. Jens is following the &lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en/blog/gardener-ext-dev">Getting started with Gardener extension development&lt;/a> tutorial, which aims to provide exactly that.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Community Call - Deploying and Developing Gardener Locally</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/03.23-gardener-community-meeting-march/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/03.23-gardener-community-meeting-march/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/timebertt">Tim Ebert&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/rfranzke">Rafael Franzke&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>So far, deploying Gardener locally was not possible end-to-end. While you certainly could run the Gardener components in a minikube or kind cluster, creating shoot clusters always required to register seeds backed by cloud provider infrastructure like AWS, Azure, etc..&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consequently, developing Gardener locally was similarly complicated, and the entry barrier for new contributors was way too high.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a previous community call (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZPAisXqjoTI&amp;amp;ab_channel=GardenerProject">Hackathon &amp;ldquo;Hack The Metal&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>), we already presented a new approach for overcoming these hurdles and complexities.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Community Call - Gardenctl-v2</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/02.17-gardener-community-meeting-february/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/02.17-gardener-community-meeting-february/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/holgerkoser">Holger Kosser&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/grolu">Lukas Gross&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/petersutter">Peter Sutter&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Watch the recording of our February 2022 Community call to see how to get started with the gardenctl-v2 and watch a walkthrough for gardenctl-v2 features. You&amp;rsquo;ll learn about targeting, secure shoot cluster access, SSH, and how to use cloud provider CLIs natively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The session is led by Lukas Gross, who begins by giving some information on the motivations behind creating a new version of gardenctl - providing secure access to shoot clustes, enabling direct usage of kubectl and cloud provider CLIs and managing cloud provider resources for SSH access.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>