<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gardener – 2022</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/</link><description>Recent content in 2022 on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Blog: Community Call - Get more computing power in Gardener by overcoming Kubelet limitations with CRI-resource-manager</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.20-gardener-community-meeting-october-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.20-gardener-community-meeting-october-2/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/ppalucki">Pawel Palucki&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/kad">Alexander D. Kanevskiy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="topics">Topics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Alexander Kanevskiy begins the community call by giving an overview of &lt;a href="https://github.com/intel/cri-resource-manager">CRI-resource-manager&lt;/a>, describing it as a &amp;ldquo;hardware aware container runtime&amp;rdquo;, and also going over what it brings to the user in terms of features and policies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pawel Palucki continues by giving details on the policy that will later be used in the demo and the use case demonstrated in it. He then goes over the &amp;ldquo;must have&amp;rdquo; features of any extension - observability and the ability to deploy and configure objects with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The demo then begins, mixed with slides giving further information at certain points regarding the installation process, static and dynamic configuration flow, healthchecks and recovery mode, and access to logs, among others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The presentation is concluded by Pawel showcasing the new features coming to CRI-resource-manager with its next releases and sharing some tips for other extension developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers at the Q&amp;amp;A session and discussion held at the end, as well as the questions asked and answered throughout the meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recording">Recording&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5a_A3furzlg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Get more computing power in Gardener with CRI-resource-manager">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Blog: Community Call - Cilium / Isovalent Presentation</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.06-gardener-community-meeting-october/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/10.06-gardener-community-meeting-october/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/raymonddejong">Raymond de Jong&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="topics">Topics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This meeting explores the uses of &lt;a href="https://cilium.io/">Cilium&lt;/a>, an open source software used to secure the network connectivity between application services deployed using Kubernetes, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/cilium/hubble/blob/master/README.md">Hubble&lt;/a>, the networking and security observability platform built on top of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Raymond de Jong begins the meeting by giving an introduction of Cillium and eBPF and how they are both used in Kubernetes networking and services. He then goes over the ways of running Cillium - either by using a supported cloud provider or by CNI chaining.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next topic introduced is the Cluster Mesh and the different use cases for it, offering high availability, shared services, local and remote service affinity, and the ability to split services.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In regards to security, being an identity-based security solution utilizing API-aware authorization, Cillium implements Hubble in order to increase its observability. Hubble combines hubble UI, hubble API and hubble Metrics - Grafana and Prometheus, in order to provide service dependency maps, detailed flow visibility and built-in metrics for operations and applications stability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The final topic covered is the Service Mesh, offering service maps and the ability to integrate Cluster Mesh features.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers at the Q&amp;amp;A session and discussion held at the end, as well as the questions asked and answered throughout the meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recording">Recording&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/46nCdVA-rsc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Cilium / Isovalent Presentation">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Blog: Community Call - Gardener Extension Development</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/06.17-gardener-community-meeting-june/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/06.17-gardener-community-meeting-june/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/jensac">Jens Schneider&lt;/a> and Lothar Gesslein.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Starting the development of a new Gardener extension can be challenging, when you are not an expert in the Gardener ecosystem yet. Therefore, the first half of this community call led by Jens Schneider aims to provide a &amp;ldquo;getting started tutorial&amp;rdquo; at a beginner level. &lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en">23Technologies&lt;/a> have developed a minimal working example for Gardener extensions, &lt;a href="https://github.com/23technologies/gardener-extension-mwe">gardener-extension-mwe&lt;/a>, hosted in a Github repository. Jens is following the &lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en/blog/gardener-ext-dev">Getting started with Gardener extension development&lt;/a> tutorial, which aims to provide exactly that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the second part of the community call, Lothar Gesslein introduces the &lt;a href="https://github.com/23technologies/gardener-extension-shoot-flux">gardener-extension-shoot-flux&lt;/a>, which allows for the automated installation of arbitrary Kubernetes resources into shoot clusters. As this extension relies on &lt;a href="https://fluxcd.io/">Flux&lt;/a>, an overview of Flux&amp;rsquo;s capabilities is also provided.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers at the Q&amp;amp;A session and discussion held at the end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find the tutorials in this community call at:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en/blog/gardener-ext-dev">Getting started with Gardener extension development&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://23technologies.cloud/en/blog/gardener-ext-shoot-flux">A Gardener Extension for universal Shoot Configuration&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers at the Q&amp;amp;A session and discussion held at the end of the meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recording">Recording&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nG2FRYL05mc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Gardener Extension Development - From scratch to the gardener-extension-shoot-flux">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Blog: Community Call - Deploying and Developing Gardener Locally</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/03.23-gardener-community-meeting-march/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/03.23-gardener-community-meeting-march/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/timebertt">Tim Ebert&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/rfranzke">Rafael Franzke&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>So far, deploying Gardener locally was not possible end-to-end. While you certainly could run the Gardener components in a minikube or kind cluster, creating shoot clusters always required to register seeds backed by cloud provider infrastructure like AWS, Azure, etc..&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consequently, developing Gardener locally was similarly complicated, and the entry barrier for new contributors was way too high.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a previous community call (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZPAisXqjoTI&amp;amp;ab_channel=GardenerProject">Hackathon &amp;ldquo;Hack The Metal&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>), we already presented a new approach for overcoming these hurdles and complexities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now we would like to present the &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/extensions/provider-local/">Local Provider Extension&lt;/a> for Gardener and show how it can be used to deploy Gardener locally, allowing you to quickly get your feet wet with the project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this session, Tim Ebert goes through the process of setting up a local Gardener cluster. After his demonstration, Rafael Franzke showcases a different approach to building your clusters locally, which, while more complicated, offers a much faster build time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find the tutorials in this community call at:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/deployment/getting_started_locally/">Deploying Gardener locally&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/getting_started_locally/">Running Gardener locally&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers in the questions asked and answered throughout the meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recording">Recording&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nV_JI8YWwY4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Deploying and Developing Gardener Locally (Without Any External Infrastructure!)">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Blog: Community Call - Gardenctl-v2</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/02.17-gardener-community-meeting-february/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2022/02.17-gardener-community-meeting-february/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="presenters">Presenters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This community call was led by &lt;a href="https://github.com/holgerkoser">Holger Kosser&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/grolu">Lukas Gross&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/petersutter">Peter Sutter&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Watch the recording of our February 2022 Community call to see how to get started with the gardenctl-v2 and watch a walkthrough for gardenctl-v2 features. You&amp;rsquo;ll learn about targeting, secure shoot cluster access, SSH, and how to use cloud provider CLIs natively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The session is led by Lukas Gross, who begins by giving some information on the motivations behind creating a new version of gardenctl - providing secure access to shoot clustes, enabling direct usage of kubectl and cloud provider CLIs and managing cloud provider resources for SSH access.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Holger Kosser then takes over in order to delve deeper into the concepts behind the implementation of gardenctl-2, going over Targeting, Gardenlogin and Cloud Provider CLIs. After that, Peter Sutter does the first demo, where he presents the main features in gardenctl-2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next part details how to get started with gardenctl, followed by another demo. The landscape requirements are also discussed, as well as future plans and enhancement requests.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find the slides for this community call at &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1WxvMwdJ1WT2YvTox8Ni_IyX4Qpsz3-87IS5M53FwSvU/edit#slide=id.p8">Google Slides&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are left with any questions regarding the content, you might find the answers at the Q&amp;amp;A session and discussion held at the end, as well as the questions asked and answered throughout the meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recording">Recording&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/U1VvyQiE3Jg" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Gardenctl-v2">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>