<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Gardener Dashboard 1.80: Streamlined Credentials, Enhanced Cluster Views, and Real-Time Updates</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/05-19-gardener-dashboard-180-streamlined-credentials-enhanced-cluster-views-and-real-time-updates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/05-19-gardener-dashboard-180-streamlined-credentials-enhanced-cluster-views-and-real-time-updates/</guid><description>&lt;p>Gardener Dashboard version 1.80 introduces several significant enhancements aimed at improving user experience, credentials management, and overall operational efficiency. These updates bring more clarity to credential handling, a smoother experience for managing large numbers of clusters, and a move towards a more reactive interface.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="unified-and-enhanced-credentials-management">Unified and Enhanced Credentials Management&lt;a class="td-heading-self-link" href="#unified-and-enhanced-credentials-management" aria-label="Heading self-link">&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>&lt;p>The management of secrets and credentials has been significantly revamped for better clarity and functionality:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Introducing CredentialsBindings:&lt;/strong> The dashboard now fully supports &lt;code>CredentialsBinding&lt;/code> resources alongside the existing &lt;code>SecretBinding&lt;/code> resources. This allows for referencing both Secrets and, in the future, Workload Identities more explicitly. While &lt;code>CredentialsBindings&lt;/code> referencing Workload Identity resources are visible for cluster creation, editing or deleting them via the dashboard is not yet supported.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Credentials&amp;rdquo; Page:&lt;/strong> The former &amp;ldquo;Secrets&amp;rdquo; page has been renamed to &amp;ldquo;Credentials.&amp;rdquo; It features a new &amp;ldquo;Kind&amp;rdquo; column and distinct icons to clearly differentiate between &lt;code>SecretBinding&lt;/code> and &lt;code>CredentialsBinding&lt;/code> types, especially useful when resources share names. The column showing the referenced credential resource name has been removed as this information is part of the binding&amp;rsquo;s details.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Contextual Information and Safeguards:&lt;/strong> When editing a secret, all its associated data is now displayed, providing better context. If an underlying secret is referenced by multiple bindings, a hint is shown to prevent unintended impacts. Deletion of a binding is prevented if the underlying secret is still in use by another binding.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Simplified Creation and Editing:&lt;/strong> New secrets created via the dashboard will now automatically generate a &lt;code>CredentialsBinding&lt;/code>. While existing &lt;code>SecretBindings&lt;/code> remain updatable, the creation of new &lt;code>SecretBindings&lt;/code> through the dashboard is no longer supported, encouraging the adoption of the more versatile &lt;code>CredentialsBinding&lt;/code>. The edit dialog for secrets now pre-fills current data, allowing for easier modification of specific fields.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Handling Missing Secrets:&lt;/strong> The UI now provides clear information and guidance if a &lt;code>CredentialsBinding&lt;/code> or &lt;code>SecretBinding&lt;/code> references a secret that no longer exists.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="revamped-cluster-list-for-improved-scalability">Revamped Cluster List for Improved Scalability&lt;a class="td-heading-self-link" href="#revamped-cluster-list-for-improved-scalability" aria-label="Heading self-link">&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Navigating and managing a large number of clusters is now more efficient:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener: Powering Enterprise Kubernetes at Scale and Europe's Sovereign Cloud Future</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/05-12-gardener-neonephos/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/05-12-gardener-neonephos/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Kubernetes ecosystem is dynamic, offering a wealth of tools to manage the complexities of modern cloud-native applications. For enterprises seeking to provision and manage Kubernetes clusters efficiently, securely, and at scale, a robust and comprehensive solution is paramount. Gardener, born from years of managing tens of thousands of clusters efficiently across diverse platforms and in demanding environments, stands out as a fully open-source choice for delivering fully managed Kubernetes Clusters as a Service. It already empowers organizations like SAP, STACKIT, T-Systems, and others (see &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/adopter">adopters&lt;/a>) and has become a core technology for &lt;a href="https://neonephos.org/projects">NeoNephos&lt;/a>, a project aimed at advancing digital autonomy in Europe (see &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=85MDID9Ju04&amp;amp;t=621s">KubeCon London 2025 Keynote&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://neonephos.org/2025/03/31/the-linux-foundation-announces-the-launch-of-neonephos-to-advance-digital-autonomy-in-europe">press announcement&lt;/a>).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Leaner Clusters, Lower Bills: How Gardener Optimized Kubernetes Compute Costs</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/04-17-leaner-clusters-lower-bills/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/04-17-leaner-clusters-lower-bills/</guid><description>&lt;p>As organizations embrace Kubernetes for managing containerized applications at scale, the underlying infrastructure costs, particularly for compute resources, become a critical factor. Gardener, the open-source Kubernetes management platform, empowers organizations like SAP, STACKIT, T-Systems, and others (see &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/adopter">adopters&lt;/a>) to operate tens of thousands of Kubernetes clusters efficiently across diverse environments. Gardener&amp;rsquo;s role as a core technology in initiatives like &lt;a href="https://neonephos.org/projects">NeoNephos&lt;/a>, aimed at advancing digital autonomy in Europe (see &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=85MDID9Ju04&amp;amp;t=621s">KubeCon London 2025 Keynote&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://neonephos.org/2025/03/31/the-linux-foundation-announces-the-launch-of-neonephos-to-advance-digital-autonomy-in-europe">press announcement&lt;/a>), further underscores the need for cost-effective and sustainable operations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gardener at KubeCon + CloudNativeCon Europe, London 2025</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/03-18-gardener-kubecon-cloudnativecon-europe-2025-announcement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/blog/2025/03-18-gardener-kubecon-cloudnativecon-europe-2025-announcement/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="gardener-at-kubecon--cloudnativecon-europe-london-2025">Gardener at KubeCon + CloudNativeCon Europe, London 2025&lt;a class="td-heading-self-link" href="#gardener-at-kubecon--cloudnativecon-europe-london-2025" aria-label="Heading self-link">&lt;/a>&lt;/h1>&lt;p>The open-source project &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/">Gardener&lt;/a> is set to showcase its cutting-edge Kubernetes-as-a-Service (KaaS) capabilities at &lt;a href="https://events.linuxfoundation.org/kubecon-cloudnativecon-europe/">KubeCon + CloudNativeCon Europe&lt;/a> 2025 in London.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gardener has been pioneering hosted control planes long before they became mainstream and is now the default choice within SAP and &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/adopter/">other organizations&lt;/a> for provisioning Kubernetes clusters.
Organizations looking to transform their Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) into a Kubernetes-as-a-Service (KaaS) platform can experience Gardener’s powerful automation, security, and multi-cloud extensibility firsthand at the event or &lt;a href="https://demo.gardener.cloud/">directly in the browser&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>