<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Monitoring on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/</link><description>Recent content in Monitoring on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Alerting</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/alerting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/alerting/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="alerting">Alerting&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Gardener uses &lt;a href="https://prometheus.io/">Prometheus&lt;/a> to gather metrics from each component. A Prometheus is deployed in each shoot control plane (on the seed) which is responsible for gathering control plane and cluster metrics. Prometheus can be configured to fire alerts based on these metrics and send them to an &lt;a href="https://prometheus.io/docs/alerting/alertmanager/">Alertmanager&lt;/a>. The Alertmanager is responsible for sending the alerts to users and operators. This document describes how to setup alerting for:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/alerting/#alerting-for-users">end-users/stakeholders/customers&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/alerting/#alerting-for-operators">operators/administrators&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="alerting-for-users">Alerting for Users&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>To receive email alerts as a user, set the following values in the shoot spec:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Connectivity</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/connectivity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/connectivity/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="connectivity">Connectivity&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="shoot-connectivity">Shoot Connectivity&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We measure the connectivity from the shoot to the API Server. This is done via the &lt;code>blackbox exporter&lt;/code> which is deployed in the shoot&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code>kube-system&lt;/code> namespace. Prometheus will scrape the &lt;code>blackbox exporter&lt;/code> and then the exporter will try to access the API Server. Metrics are exposed if the connection was successful or not. This can be seen in the &lt;code>Kubernetes Control Plane Status&lt;/code> dashboard under the &lt;code>API Server Connectivity&lt;/code> panel. The &lt;code>shoot&lt;/code> line represents the connectivity from the shoot.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Profiling</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/profiling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/monitoring/profiling/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="profiling-gardener-components">Profiling Gardener Components&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Similar to Kubernetes, Gardener components support profiling using &lt;a href="https://golang.org/doc/diagnostics#profiling">standard Go tools&lt;/a> for analyzing CPU and memory usage by different code sections and more.
This document shows how to enable and use profiling handlers with Gardener components.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enabling profiling handlers and the ports on which they are exposed differs between components.
However, once the handlers are enabled, they provide profiles via the same HTTP endpoint paths, from which you can retrieve them via &lt;code>curl&lt;/code>/&lt;code>wget&lt;/code> or directly using &lt;code>go tool pprof&lt;/code>.
(You might need to use &lt;code>kubectl port-forward&lt;/code> in order to access HTTP endpoints of Gardener components running in clusters.)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>