<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Contribute on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/</link><description>Recent content in Contribute on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Configuration and Usage</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/configuration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/configuration/</guid><description>Gardener Configuration and Usage Gardener automates the full lifecycle of Kubernetes clusters as a service. Additionally, it has several extension points allowing external controllers to plug-in to the lifecycle. As a consequence, there are several configuration options for the various custom resources that are partially required.
This document describes the
configuration and usage of Gardener as operator/administrator. configuration and usage of Gardener as end-user/stakeholder/customer. Configuration and Usage of Gardener as Operator/Administrator When we use the terms &amp;ldquo;operator/administrator&amp;rdquo; we refer to both the people deploying and operating Gardener.</description></item><item><title>Contribution Guide</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/10-contribution_guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/10-contribution_guide/</guid><description>Contributing to Gardener Code of conduct All members of the Gardener community must abide by the CNCF Code of Conduct. Only by respecting each other can we develop a productive, collaborative community. Instances of abusive, harassing, or otherwise unacceptable behavior may be reported by contacting gardener.opensource@sap.com and/or a Gardener project maintainer.
Contributing Gardener uses GitHub to manage reviews of pull requests.
If you are a new contributor see: Steps to Contribute</description></item><item><title>Dependencies</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/20-testing_and_dependencies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/20-testing_and_dependencies/</guid><description>Testing We follow the BDD-style testing principles and are leveraging the Ginkgo framework along with Gomega as matcher library. In order to execute the existing tests, you can use
make test # runs tests make verify # runs static code checks and test There is an additional command for analyzing the code coverage of the tests. Ginkgo will generate standard Golang cover profiles which will be translated into a HTML file by the Go Cover Tool.</description></item><item><title>Deploy into AKS</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/aks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/aks/</guid><description>Deploying the previous Gardener versions and a Seed into an AKS cluster This document demonstrates how to install Gardener into an existing AKS cluster. We&amp;rsquo;ll use a single cluster to host both Gardener and a Seed to the same cluster for the sake of simplicity .
Please note that this document is to provide you an example installation and is not to be used in a production environment since there are some certificates hardcoded, non-HA and non-TLS-enabled etcd setup.</description></item><item><title>Environment</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/local_setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/local_setup/</guid><description>Preparing the Setup Conceptually, all Gardener components are designated to run inside as a Pod inside a Kubernetes cluster. The API server extends the Kubernetes API via the user-aggregated API server concepts. However, if you want to develop it, you may want to work locally with the Gardener without building a Docker image and deploying it to a cluster each and every time. That means that the Gardener runs outside a Kubernetes cluster which requires providing a Kubeconfig in your local filesystem and point the Gardener to it when starting it (see below).</description></item><item><title>Process</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/37-process/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/37-process/</guid><description>Creating a new Feature If you want to contribute to the Gardener, please do that always on a dedicated branch on your own fork named after the purpose of the code changes, for example feature/helm-integration. Please do not forget to rebase your branch regularly.
If you have finished your work, please create a pull request based on master. It will be reviewed and merged if no further changes are requested from you.</description></item><item><title>Security Release Process</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/12-security_guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/contribute/10_code/12-security_guide/</guid><description>Gardener Security Release Process Gardener is a growing community of volunteers and users. The Gardener community has adopted this security disclosure and response policy to ensure we responsibly handle critical issues.
Gardener Security Team Security vulnerabilities should be handled quickly and sometimes privately. The primary goal of this process is to reduce the total time users are vulnerable to publicly known exploits. The Gardener Security Team is responsible for organizing the entire response including internal communication and external disclosure but will need help from relevant developers and release managers to successfully run this process.</description></item></channel></rss>