<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Architecture on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/architecture/</link><description>Recent content in Architecture on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dashboard</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/components/dashboard/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/components/dashboard/</guid><description>Gardener Dashboard
Demo Development Setup Install Install all dependencies
yarn Configuration KUBECONFIG If the dashboard is not running in the Garden Cluster you have to point the kubeconfig to Garden Cluster. This can be done in the default kubeconfig file in ${HOME}/.kube/config or by the KUBECONFIG environment variable.
GARDENER_CONFIG The configuration file of the Gardener Dashboard can be specified as first command line argument or as environment variable GARDENER_CONFIG at the server process.</description></item><item><title>gardenctl</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/components/gardenctl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/components/gardenctl/</guid><description>Gardenctl
What is gardenctl? gardenctl is a command-line client for administrative purposes for the Gardener. It facilitates the administration of one or many garden, seed and shoot clusters, e.g. to check for issues which occured in one of these clusters. Details about the concept behind the Gardener are described in the Gardener wiki.
Installation gardenctl is shipped for mac and linux in a binary format.
Option 1: Install the latest release with Homebrew (macOS and Linux) as follows:</description></item><item><title>kubify</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/components/kubify/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/components/kubify/</guid><description>Kubify Kubify is a Terraform based provisioning project for setting up production ready Kubernetes clusters on public and private Cloud infrastructures. Kubify currently supports:
OpenStack AWS Azure Key features of Kubify are:
Kubernetes v1.10.12 Etcd v3.3.10 multi master node setup Etcd backup and restore Supports rolling updates To start using or developing Kubify locally See our documentation in the /docs repository or find the main documentation here.</description></item></channel></rss>