<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Networking on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/</link><description>Recent content in Networking on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DNS Management</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/dns-managment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/dns-managment/</guid><description>External DNS Management The main artefact of this project is the DNS controller manager for managing DNS records, also nicknamed as the Gardener &amp;ldquo;DNS Controller&amp;rdquo;.
It contains provisioning controllers for creating DNS records in one of the DNS cloud services
Amazon Route53, Google CloudDNS, AliCloud DNS, Azure DNS, OpenStack Designate, Cloudflare DNS, Infoblox, Netlify DNS, and source controllers for services and ingresses to create DNS entries by annotations.</description></item><item><title>Certificates Management</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/cert-managment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/cert-managment/</guid><description>cert-management
Manages TLS certificates in Kubernetes clusters using custom resources.
In a multi-cluster environment like Gardener, using existing open source projects for certificate management like cert-manager becomes cumbersome. With this project the separation of concerns between multiple clusters is realized more easily. The cert-controller-manager runs in a secured cluster where the issuer secrets are stored. At the same time it watches an untrusted source cluster and can provide certificates for it.</description></item><item><title>Network Policies</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/network_policies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/networking/network_policies/</guid><description>Network Policies in Gardener As Seed clusters can host the Kubernetes control planes of many Shoot clusters, it is necessary to isolate the control planes from each other for security reasons. Besides deploying each control plane in its own namespace, Gardener creates network policies to also isolate the networks. Essentially, network policies make sure that pods can only talk to other pods over the network they are supposed to. As such, network policies are an important part of Gardener&amp;rsquo;s tenant isolation.</description></item></channel></rss>