<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Monitoring on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/</link><description>Recent content in Monitoring on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Alerting</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/alerting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/alerting/</guid><description>Alerting Gardener uses Prometheus to gather metrics from each component. A Prometheus is deployed in each shoot control plane (on the seed) which is responsible for gathering control plane and cluster metrics. Prometheus can be configured to fire alerts based on these metrics and send them to an alertmanager. The alertmanager is responsible for sending the alerts to users and operators. This document describes how to setup alerting for:
end-users/stakeholders/customers</description></item><item><title>Extending the Monitoring Stack</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/extending/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/extending/</guid><description>Extending the Monitoring Stack This document provides instructions to extend the Shoot cluster monitoring stack by integrating new scrape targets, alerts and dashboards.
Please ensure that you have understood the basic principles of Prometheus and its ecosystem before you continue.
:bangbang: The purpose of the monitoring stack is to observe the behaviour of the control plane and the system components deployed by Gardener onto the worker nodes. Monitoring of custom workloads running in the cluster is out of scope.</description></item><item><title>Operator Alerts</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/operator-alerts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/operator-alerts/</guid><description>Operator Alerts Alertname Severity Type Description ApiServerUnreachableViaKubernetesService critical shoot The Api server has been unreachable for 3 minutes via the kubernetes service in the shoot. CoreDNSDown critical shoot CoreDNS could not be found. Cluster DNS resolution will not work. ApiServerNotReachable blocker seed API server not reachable via external endpoint: {{ $labels.instance }}. KubeApiserverDown blocker seed All API server replicas are down/unreachable, or all API server could not be found.</description></item><item><title>User Alerts</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/user_alerts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/documentation/concepts/monitoring/user_alerts/</guid><description>User Alerts Alertname Severity Type Description ApiServerUnreachableViaKubernetesService critical shoot The Api server has been unreachable for 3 minutes via the kubernetes service in the shoot. CoreDNSDown critical shoot CoreDNS could not be found. Cluster DNS resolution will not work. ApiServerNotReachable blocker seed API server not reachable via external endpoint: {{ $labels.instance }}. KubeApiServerTooManyOpenFileDescriptors warning seed The API server ({{ $labels.</description></item></channel></rss>