<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>How-To Guides on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/</link><description>Recent content in How-To Guides on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Landscape Setup</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/landscape-setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/landscape-setup/</guid><description>&amp;mdash;DEPRECATED&amp;mdash; This project is outdated and won&amp;rsquo;t be updated anymore. Please use https://github.com/gardener/garden-setup instead!
Gardener Setup Scripts This README is the installation manual for a simple Gardener setup. The installation scripts in this repo are embedded in a configuration template in the landscape-setup-template project. You can find further information there.
We do recommend this simplified setup for demonstration purposes only. For productive workloads we do recommend that all components (Gardener/Seed/Shoot) run in their own IaaS accounts and that network policies are enabled and properly tested on the seed clusters.</description></item><item><title>Manage DNS Providers</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/dns_providers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/dns_providers/</guid><description>DNS Providers Introduction Gardener can manage DNS records on your behalf, so that you can request them via different resource types (see here) within the shoot cluster. The domains for which you are permitted to request records, are however restricted and depend on the DNS provider configuration.
Shoot provider By default, every shoot cluster is equipped with a default provider. It is the very same provider that manages the shoot cluster&amp;rsquo;s kube-apiserver public DNS record (DNS address in your Kubeconfig).</description></item><item><title>Request DNS Names</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/dns_names/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/dns_names/</guid><description>Request DNS Names in Shoot Clusters Introduction Within a shoot cluster, it is possible to request DNS records via the following resource types:
Ingress Service DNSEntry It is necessary that the Gardener installation your shoot cluster runs in is equipped with a shoot-dns-service extension. This extension uses the seed&amp;rsquo;s dns management infrastructure to maintain DNS names for shoot clusters. Please ask your Gardener operator if the extension is available in your environment.</description></item><item><title>Request X.509 Certificates</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/request_cert/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/request_cert/</guid><description>Request X.509 Certificates Introduction Dealing with applications on Kubernetes which offer service endpoints (e.g. HTTP) may also require you to enable a secured communication via SSL/TLS. Gardener let&amp;rsquo;s you request a commonly trusted X.509 certificate for your application endpoint. Furthermore, Gardener takes care about the renewal process for your requested certificate.
Let&amp;rsquo;s get the basics straight first. If this is too long for you, you can read below how to get certificates by</description></item><item><title>Trigger Shoot operations</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/trigger-shoot-operations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.13.2/guides/administer_shoots/trigger-shoot-operations/</guid><description>Trigger shoot operations You can trigger a few explicit operations by annotating the Shoot with an operation annotation. This might allow you to induct certain behavior without the need to change the Shoot specification. Some of the operations can also not be caused by changing something in the shoot specification because they can&amp;rsquo;t properly be reflected here.
Please note: If .spec.maintenance.confineSpecUpdateRollout=true then the only way to trigger a shoot reconciliation is by setting the reconcile operation, see below.</description></item></channel></rss>