<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gardener – Deployment</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/other-components/etcd-druid/deployment/</link><description>Recent content in Deployment on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/other-components/etcd-druid/deployment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Feature Gates in Etcd-Druid</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/other-components/etcd-druid/deployment/feature-gates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/other-components/etcd-druid/deployment/feature-gates/</guid><description>
&lt;h1 id="feature-gates-in-etcd-druid">Feature Gates in Etcd-Druid&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This page contains an overview of the various feature gates an administrator can specify on etcd-druid.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Feature gates are a set of key=value pairs that describe etcd-druid features. You can turn these features on or off by passing them to the &lt;code>--feature-gates&lt;/code> CLI flag in the etcd-druid command.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following tables are a summary of the feature gates that you can set on etcd-druid.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The “Since” column contains the etcd-druid release when a feature is introduced or its release stage is changed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The “Until” column, if not empty, contains the last etcd-druid release in which you can still use a feature gate.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a feature is in the &lt;em>Alpha&lt;/em> or &lt;em>Beta&lt;/em> state, you can find the feature listed in the Alpha/Beta feature gate table.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a feature is stable you can find all stages for that feature listed in the Graduated/Deprecated feature gate table.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Graduated/Deprecated feature gate table also lists deprecated and withdrawn features.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="feature-gates-for-alpha-or-beta-features">Feature Gates for Alpha or Beta Features&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Default&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Stage&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Since&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Until&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>UseEtcdWrapper&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>false&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>Alpha&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>0.19&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h2 id="feature-gates-for-graduated-or-deprecated-features">Feature Gates for Graduated or Deprecated Features&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Default&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Stage&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Since&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Until&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h2 id="using-a-feature">Using a Feature&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A feature can be in &lt;em>Alpha&lt;/em>, &lt;em>Beta&lt;/em> or &lt;em>GA&lt;/em> stage.
An &lt;em>Alpha&lt;/em> feature means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Disabled by default.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Might be buggy. Enabling the feature may expose bugs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support for feature may be dropped at any time without notice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The API may change in incompatible ways in a later software release without notice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recommended for use only in short-lived testing clusters, due to increased
risk of bugs and lack of long-term support.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>A &lt;em>Beta&lt;/em> feature means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Enabled by default.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The feature is well tested. Enabling the feature is considered safe.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support for the overall feature will not be dropped, though details may change.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The schema and/or semantics of objects may change in incompatible ways in a
subsequent beta or stable release. When this happens, we will provide instructions
for migrating to the next version. This may require deleting, editing, and
re-creating API objects. The editing process may require some thought.
This may require downtime for applications that rely on the feature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recommended for only non-critical uses because of potential for
incompatible changes in subsequent releases.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Please do try &lt;em>Beta&lt;/em> features and give feedback on them!
After they exit beta, it may not be practical for us to make more changes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A &lt;em>General Availability&lt;/em> (GA) feature is also referred to as a &lt;em>stable&lt;/em> feature. It means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The feature is always enabled; you cannot disable it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The corresponding feature gate is no longer needed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stable versions of features will appear in released software for many subsequent versions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="list-of-feature-gates">List of Feature Gates&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Feature&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Description&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;code>UseEtcdWrapper&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Enables the use of etcd-wrapper image and a compatible version of etcd-backup-restore, along with component-specific configuration changes necessary for the usage of the etcd-wrapper image.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item></channel></rss>