<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shoot Operations on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/</link><description>Recent content in Shoot Operations on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Controlling the Kubernetes Versions for Specific Worker Pools</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/worker_pool_k8s_versions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/worker_pool_k8s_versions/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="controlling-the-kubernetes-versions-for-specific-worker-pools">Controlling the Kubernetes Versions for Specific Worker Pools&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Since Gardener &lt;code>v1.36&lt;/code>, worker pools can have different Kubernetes versions specified than the control plane.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In earlier Gardener versions, all worker pools inherited the Kubernetes version of the control plane. Once the Kubernetes version of the control plane was modified, all worker pools have been updated as well (either by rolling the nodes in case of a minor version change, or in-place for patch version changes).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shoot Credentials Rotation</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_credentials_rotation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_credentials_rotation/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="credentials-rotation-for-shoot-clusters">Credentials Rotation for Shoot Clusters&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>There are a lot of different credentials for &lt;code>Shoot&lt;/code>s to make sure that the various components can communicate with each other and to make sure it is usable and operable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This page explains how the varieties of credentials can be rotated so that the cluster can be considered secure.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="user-provided-credentials">User-Provided Credentials&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="cloud-provider-keys">Cloud Provider Keys&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>End-users must provide credentials such that Gardener and Kubernetes controllers can communicate with the respective cloud provider APIs in order to perform infrastructure operations.
For example, Gardener uses them to set up and maintain the networks, security groups, subnets, etc., while the &lt;a href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/architecture/cloud-controller/">cloud-controller-manager&lt;/a> uses them to reconcile load balancers and routes, and the &lt;a href="https://kubernetes-csi.github.io/docs/">CSI controller&lt;/a> uses them to reconcile volumes and disks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shoot Kubernetes and Operating System Versioning in Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_versions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_versions/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="shoot-kubernetes-and-operating-system-versioning-in-gardener">Shoot Kubernetes and Operating System Versioning in Gardener&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="motivation">Motivation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>On the one hand-side, Gardener is responsible for managing the Kubernetes and the Operating System (OS) versions of its Shoot clusters.
On the other hand-side, Gardener needs to be configured and updated based on the availability and support of the Kubernetes and Operating System version it provides.
For instance, the Kubernetes community releases &lt;strong>minor&lt;/strong> versions roughly every three months and usually maintains &lt;strong>three minor&lt;/strong> versions (the current and the last two) with bug fixes and security updates.
Patch releases are done more frequently.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shoot Updates and Upgrades</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_updates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_updates/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="shoot-updates-and-upgrades">Shoot Updates and Upgrades&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This document describes what happens during shoot updates (changes incorporated in a newly deployed Gardener version) and during shoot upgrades (changes for version controllable by end-users).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="updates">Updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Updates to all aspects of the shoot cluster happen when the gardenlet reconciles the &lt;code>Shoot&lt;/code> resource.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="when-are-reconciliations-triggered">When are Reconciliations Triggered&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Generally, when you change the specification of your &lt;code>Shoot&lt;/code> the reconciliation will start immediately, potentially updating your cluster.
Please note that you can also confine the reconciliation triggered due to your specification updates to the cluster&amp;rsquo;s maintenance time window. Please find more information in &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot/shoot_maintenance/#confine-specification-changesupdates-roll-out">Confine Specification Changes/Updates Roll Out&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Supported Kubernetes Versions</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/supported_k8s_versions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/supported_k8s_versions/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="supported-kubernetes-versions">Supported Kubernetes Versions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Currently, Gardener supports the following Kubernetes versions:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="garden-clusters">Garden Clusters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The minimum version of a garden cluster that can be used to run Gardener is &lt;strong>&lt;code>1.25.x&lt;/code>&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="seed-clusters">Seed Clusters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The minimum version of a seed cluster that can be connected to Gardener is &lt;strong>&lt;code>1.25.x&lt;/code>&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="shoot-clusters">Shoot Clusters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Gardener itself is capable of spinning up clusters with Kubernetes versions &lt;strong>&lt;code>1.25&lt;/code>&lt;/strong> up to &lt;strong>&lt;code>1.32&lt;/code>&lt;/strong>.
However, the concrete versions that can be used for shoot clusters depend on the installed provider extension.
Consequently, please consult the documentation of your provider extension to see which Kubernetes versions are supported for shoot clusters.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Trigger Shoot Operations Through Annotations</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_operations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/shoot-operations/shoot_operations/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="trigger-shoot-operations-through-annotations">Trigger Shoot Operations Through Annotations&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>You can trigger a few explicit operations by annotating the &lt;code>Shoot&lt;/code> with an operation annotation.
This might allow you to induct certain behavior without the need to change the &lt;code>Shoot&lt;/code> specification.
Some of the operations can also not be caused by changing something in the shoot specification because they can&amp;rsquo;t properly be reflected here.
Note that once the triggered operation is considered by the controllers, the annotation will be automatically removed and you have to add it each time you want to trigger the operation.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>