<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gardener – FAQ</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/</link><description>Recent content in FAQ on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Can I run privileged containers?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/privileged-containers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/privileged-containers/</guid><description>
&lt;p>While it is possible, we highly recommend not to use privileged containers in your productive environment. You can find more information &lt;a href="https://pages.github.tools.sap/kubernetes/gardener/docs/guides/pod-node-operations/deploy-priv-pod/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Can Kubernetes upgrade automatically?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/automatic-upgrade/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/automatic-upgrade/</guid><description>
&lt;p>There is no automatic migration of major/minor versions of Kubernetes. You need to update your clusters manually or press the &lt;em>Upgrade&lt;/em> button in the Dashboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before updating a cluster you should be aware of the potential errors this might cause. The following video will dive into a Kubernetes outage in production that Monzo experienced, its causes and effects, and the architectural and operational lessons learned.&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OUYTNywPk-s" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>It is therefore recommended to first update your test cluster and validate it before performing changes on a productive environment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Can you backup your Kubernetes cluster resources?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/backup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/backup/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Backing up your Kubernetes cluster is possible through the use of specialized software like &lt;a href="https://velero.io/">Velero&lt;/a>. Velero consists of a server side component and a client tool that allow you to backup or restore all objects in your cluster, as well as the cluster resources and persistent volumes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information on cluster backup, see &lt;a href="https://pages.github.tools.sap/kubernetes/gardener/docs/guides/backup-restore/">Backup and Restore of Kubernetes Objects&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Can you migrate the content of one cluster to another cluster?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/automatic-migrate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/automatic-migrate/</guid><description>
&lt;p>The migration of clusters or content from one cluster to another is out of scope for the Gardener project. For such scenarios you may consider using tools like &lt;a href="https://velero.io/">Velero&lt;/a>. More information can be found at &lt;a href="https://pages.github.tools.sap/kubernetes/gardener/docs/015-guides/010-additional-software/backup-restore/">Backup and Restore of Kubernetes Objects&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: How can you deploy Gardener locally?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/gardener-locally/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/gardener-locally/</guid><description>
&lt;p>If you need information on how to deploy your cluster on your local machine, a step-by-step tutorial can be found at &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/development/getting_started_locally/">Running Gardener locally&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can also watch the recorded &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nV_JI8YWwY4&amp;amp;ab_channel=GardenerProject">Community Call&lt;/a> to get a better understanding of the process.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: How can you get the status of a shoot API server?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/clusterhealthz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/clusterhealthz/</guid><description>
&lt;p>There are two ways to get the health information of a shoot API server.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Try to reach the public endpoint of the shoot API server via
&lt;code>&amp;quot;https://api.&amp;lt;shoot-name&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;project-name&amp;gt;.shoot.&amp;lt;canary|office|live&amp;gt;.k8s-hana.ondemand.com/healthz&amp;quot;&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The endpoint is secured, therefore you need to authenticate via basic auth or client cert. Both are available in the admin kubeconfig of the shoot cluster. Note that with those credentials you have full (admin) access to the cluster, therefore it is highly recommended to create custom credentials with some RBAC rules and bindings which only allow access to the /healthz endpoint.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fetch the shoot resource of your cluster via the programmatic API of the Gardener and get the availability information from the status.
You need a kubeconfig for the Garden cluster, which you can get via the Gardener dashboard. Then you could fetch your shoot resource and query for the availability information via:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-sh" data-lang="sh">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>kubectl get shoot &amp;lt;shoot-name&amp;gt; -o json | jq -r &lt;span style="color:#a31515">&amp;#39;.status.conditions[] | select(.type==&amp;#34;APIServerAvailable&amp;#34;)&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The availability information in the second scenario is collected by the Gardener. If you want to collect the information independently from Gardener, you should choose the first scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to archive a simple pull monitor in the AvS for a shoot cluster, you also need to use the first scenario, because with it you have a stable endpoint for the API server which you can query.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: How can you monitor your Kubernetes deployments?</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/dynatrace/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/dynatrace/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Monitoring your Kubernetes deployments is possible through the use of Dynatrace or Prometheus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://pages.github.tools.sap/apm/solutions/k8s">This document&lt;/a> describes how to connect Dynatrace to your Kubernetes based deployments on SAP Cloud Platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://pages.github.tools.sap/kubernetes/gardener/docs/guides/prometheus/">Here&lt;/a> you can also read about monitoring your Kubernetes applications with Prometheus.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Reconciliation</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/reconciliation-impact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/docs/faq/reconciliation-impact/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-impacted-during-a-reconciliation">What is impacted during a reconciliation?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Infrastructure and DNSRecord reconciliation are only done during usual reconciliation if there were relevant changes. Otherwise, they are only done during maintenance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-do-you-steer-a-reconciliation">How do you steer a reconciliation?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Reconciliation is bound to the maintenance time window of a cluster. This means that your shoot will be reconciled regularly, without need for input.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Outside of the maintenance time window your shoot will only reconcile if you change the specification or if you explicitly trigger it. To learn how, see &lt;a href="https://gardener.cloud/docs/gardener/usage/shoot_operations/">Trigger shoot operations&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>