<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>How-To Guides on Gardener</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/</link><description>Recent content in How-To Guides on Gardener</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>HTTPS with self Signed Certificate</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/applications/https/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/applications/https/</guid><description>Configuring ingress with front-end TLS It is alyways recommended to enable encryption for services to prevent traffic interception and man-in-the-middle attacks - even in DEV environments.
You should configure front-end Transport Layer Security (TLS) so that the ingress controller can secure access to a service from the client to the load balancer by using HTTPS.
We will use basic procedure here. If your configuration requires advanced security options, please refer to official CloudFlare&amp;rsquo;s cfssl documentation.</description></item><item><title>Landscape Setup</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/landscape-setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/landscape-setup/</guid><description>&amp;mdash;DEPRECATED&amp;mdash; This project is outdated and won&amp;rsquo;t be updated anymore. Please use https://github.com/gardener/garden-setup instead!
Gardener Setup Scripts This README is the installation manual for a simple Gardener setup. The installation scripts in this repo are embedded in a configuration template in the landscape-setup-template project. You can find further information there.
We do recommend this simplified setup for demonstration purposes only. For productive workloads we do recommend that all components (Gardener/Seed/Shoot) run in their own IaaS accounts and that network policies are enabled and properly tested on the seed clusters.</description></item><item><title>Trigger Shoot operations</title><link>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/administer_shoots/trigger-shoot-operations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gardener.cloud/v1.11.0/guides/administer_shoots/trigger-shoot-operations/</guid><description>Trigger shoot operations You can trigger a few explicit operations by annotating the Shoot with an operation annotation. This might allow you to induct certain behavior without the need to change the Shoot specification. Some of the operations can also not be caused by changing something in the shoot specification because they can&amp;rsquo;t properly be reflected here.
Please note: If .spec.maintenance.confineSpecUpdateRollout=true then the only way to trigger a shoot reconciliation is by setting the reconcile operation, see below.</description></item></channel></rss>